All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. 17th day of the עומר. Omer.
We are doing דף יא Daf Yud Aleph today. We start at
the very bottom of י עמוד ב, Yud Amud Bet, a new
פרק. perek. So the last פרק perek dealt with a lot of
these questions about the stages of קדושה, kedusha, that once you sanctify
something there's מעילה meilah and then different stages as it gets more
of a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf as it were, when it goes
into the כלי keli or זריקת הדם zerikat hadam and so on
are other statuses relevant. Now we take a look at cases where
there is no מעילה meilah because things are no longer fit for
the מזבח. mizbeach. I want to remind you before we start that
at the very beginning of the first פרק perek we taught that
once something is sanctified, even if at a certain point it becomes
unfit, like for example, there's a thought of פיגול pigul or that
the meat becomes טמא tamei and so on, פיגול pigul still applies.
Not only that,
מעילה meilah still applies. Not only that, but it might apply longer
because since it never becomes מותר לכהנים muttar lakohanim like the meat,
right, if we're dealing with קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim at least, then
it never becomes מותר. muttar. So the fact that it is פסול
pasul does not take it out of the category of מעילה. meilah.
Once it's sanctified, as long as until it unless it becomes מותר
muttar for אכילה, achila, it remains מעילה. meilah. With that in mind,
let's take a look at our משניות mishnayot in our פרק. perek.
As you can see, just by glancing at the next דף, daf,
there's a lot of little גמרות, gemarot, so there's a lot of
משניות mishnayot
in this discussion about things that do not have מעילה meilah because
they are somehow not fit. So let's take a look. Again, bottom
of י עמוד ב. Yud Amud Bet. ולד חטאת, vlad chatat, if
you have either these standard examples of a חטאת chatat that has
to be למיתה lemitah because it can no longer do its function
of כפרה. kapara. So ולד חטאת ותמורת חטאת, vlad chatat utmurat chatat,
so either the child of a חטאת, chatat, חטאת chatat were females,
and you cannot use the child for כפרה kapara to do that
function, or the תמורה tmurah of a חטאת. chatat. Similar idea, only
the original animal can function for כפרה, kapara, not the תמורה. tmurah.
וחטאת שמתו בעליה, vechatat shemetu bealeha, or the owners are died, so
there's no longer any function of כפרה. kapara. In all of those
examples, the הלכה halacha is ימותו. yamutu. That's a classic teaching that
we've had before about the cases about a חטאת שמתה chatat shemetah
that can no longer function as כפרה kapara or can never function
and therefore it has to be allowed to die. Now, there are
two other cases of חטאת שמתה chatat shemetah but those depend on
the circumstances a little bit more. שעבר שנתה ואבדה, she'avar shnata ve'avda,
let's say it is more than a year old, okay, or it
got lost ונמצאת בעלת מום venimtset ba'alat mum and now it has
a מום. mum. You lost it, it was תמים, tamim, now it
has a מום. mum. אם משכיפרו הבעלים תמות, im mishekippru habaalim tamut,
if the owners have already already been atoned for,
meaning that they brought another one in its place, then you have
to let it die. Okay, so then it also is in the
category of חטאת שמתה. chatat shemetah. Just for a second, what's the
difference between עבר שנתה avar shnata and נתכפרו באחר? nitkaper beacher?
Yeah, well, hold on one minute.
Yes. The reason is because
of עבר שנתה avar shnata and it was lost are both scenarios
where it's possible it wouldn't have to die. What's the scenario? Because
these are things that originally were good. Okay? And the עבר שנתה
avar shnata is just you waited too long. So if it became
a בעלת מום, ba'alat mum, you could be פודה podeh it for
something else if you didn't actually נתכפרו באחר. nitkaper beacher.
Meaning it was within the first year?
No, if
it
was עבר שנתה, avar shnata, it's more than a year old. If
you're not yet, if you have not yet brought another קרבן, korban,
you can wait till this animal becomes a בעלת מום ba'alat mum
and just be פודה podeh it. Okay? Being עבר שנתה avar shnata
is not like these other things. ולד חטאת, vlad chatat, תמורת חטאת
tmurat chatat is never fit for כפרה. kapara. בעלים ba'alim die, there's
no longer relevant כפרה. kapara. עבר שנתה avar shnata is like, it's
almost like a מום, mum, right? There's just a problem, you can't
bring it because it's too old. So fine, so wait until it
really gets a מום mum and be פודה. podeh. Okay? Or if
it got lost and you had waited and you had found it,
you could have used it or even if it had a מום
mum and it was around you, you could have been פודה podeh
it and used it. So the last two cases where it was
more than a year old or it was lost are scenarios where
there are possible, you could have used it if you would have
found it or if you would have waited for it to get
a מום, mum, or if it had a מום mum and it
was around you, you could have been פודה podeh it and used
it. But you didn't do that. You went ahead and you just
brought another one. And afterwards, and well the one, the case that's
more than a year older, it was already there, but you didn't
wait to for it to get a מום, mum, you brought another
one. Or it was lost, you brought another one, and then you
found the one that was missing. Now it has a מום, mum,
but too late. You already brought another one. So both of those
are variations of נתכפרו באחר. nitkaper beacher. Okay? So in those cases,
if you went ahead and did bring another one, then תמות, tamut,
then again it's a case that the owner's already got their atonement
with something else and this can no longer be used. You have
to let them die.
And now... ואינה עושה תמורה. ve'eina osa tmura. If
it cannot make a תמורה tmura although you have תמורה tmura by
a בעל מום, ba'al mum, right, רע בטוב או טוב ברע, ra
be'tov o tov be'ra, you remember that all מסכת תמורה, masechet tmura,
but this is a something that its קדושה kedusha
basically tells says that it has to die, not just it's not
קרבן korban like a בעל מום, ba'al mum, but this is a
type of a thing that it cannot make a תמורה. tmura. Okay,
so if you tried to do a תמורה, tmura, that's not a
good—I mean, it's a good thing you can't make a תמורה. tmura.
תמורה tmura is a negative thing, it's an עבירה, aveira, whatever, but
anyway, it doesn't have the power, the קדושה kedusha to transfer to
another קרבן korban because it is basically
its only status is that it's going to die. Now, because its
only status is that it's going to die, ולא נהנין ולא מועלין,
ve'lo nehenin ve'lo mo'alin, there's no—you're not allowed to be נהנה neheneh
from it rabbinically, because obviously it still has קדושה, kedusha, but nevertheless,
there is no מעילה. me'ila. Okay, and that is why it's relevant
for us, there is no מעילה, me'ila, although as I said before
we started this, that a קרבן korban could become פסול, pasul, it
could become פיגול pigul or whatever and it no longer is able
to be used and it has to be burnt or whatever, that
is—that's true, there's still מעילה, me'ila, but something that basically is headed
to
die is completely—that it has like no relevance to that קדושה. kedusha.
Even a קרבן korban that's פסול, pasul, you burn it, there's a
way you treat it in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's, you
know, פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim
and so on. This type of thing is completely removed from the
category of קדשי השם kodshei Hashem and therefore there is no מעילה.
me'ila. It's completely removed, and—and you should say still why not לא
נהנין? lo nehenin?
Okay, rabbinically. I mean, it's still true that it has קדושה, kedusha,
but in the category of קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, which are things
at the very sort of high level, as we say, this type
of thing which is תמות tamut is out of that. ואם עד
שלא כיפרו הבעלים, ve'im ad shelo kiperu haba'alim, top of יו"ד א'
עמ' א', Yud Aleph Amud Aleph, if the owners have not gotten
their atonement yet for the last two cases, so there's a potential
for using for, you know, them getting a מום mum and using
the proceeds, so those cases, תירעה עד שתיסתאב, teira'eh ad shetistave, what
the normal advice would be, wait for them to get a מום,
mum, ותימכר ve'timacher and sell it, ויביא בדמיה אחרת ve'yavi bidmeha acheret
and use the proceeds for another one, so basically redeem it if
it has a מום, mum, either by selling it, redeeming it on
your own money and so on, fine, and those cases where it
is still possibly able to be used for a קרבן, korban, עושה
תמורה ומועלין בה. osa tmura u'mo'alin bah. It can make a תמורה
tmura because that קדושה kedusha eventually could transfer to another animal that
could be used, right, if you basically redeem it and you used
the money to buy another one, then it actually becomes a viable
חטאת chatas and therefore also there is going to be מעילה me'ila
as well. מעילה me'ila really applies by the way, it doesn't need
to have קדושת קרבן kedushat korban to be a מעילה. me'ila. קדושת
דמים kedushat damim is also, I mean, this sort of דמי המזבח,
dmei hamizbe'ach, it's a value that's going to ultimately get transferred into
a קרבן. korban. But nevertheless, it doesn't have to be קדושת קרבן
kedushat korban to be מעילה. me'ila. But what it can't be is
basically—and even a קרבן פסול korban pasul as we've said, but what
it can't be is a קרבן korban that basically is completely, you
know, useless is the wrong word, but anyway, it's תמות, tamut, that
is basically completely rejected. Okay, so let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. Well, let's read this short גמרא Gemara and then
you'll ask your question. גמרא Gemara is very straightforward. מאי שנא רישא
דלא קמפליג ומאי שנא סיפא דקמפליג. mai shna reisha de'lo kamaplig u'mai
shna seifa de'kamaplig.
Why in the beginning does it just list three and say תמות,
tamut, and at the end it says oh and if these two
things happened and נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher תמות, tamut, but otherwise not?
So the answer is self-evident because it matters. So it
says רישא פסיקא ליה. reisha psika lei. In the first three cases,
it doesn't matter, there's no scenario of
לא נתכפרו באחר. lo nitkapru be'acher. ולד חטאת velad chatas and תמורת
חטאת tmurat chatas is always מיתה misa regardless, and מתו בעליה, metu
ba'aleha, the owners dead, there can't be נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru be'acher. So
those cases there are no ways to make any distinction. I don't
know. סיפא לא פסיקא ליה. seifa lo psika lei. In the end,
there are—it matters, the circumstances, whether it's נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher or
not. I don't know. Okay, now גמרא Gemara just asks another very
short, simple question. התם לגבי תמורה. hatam legabei tmura. This exact same
משנה mishna appeared in תמורה. tmura. Why do we teach it both
in מעילה me'ila and in תמורה? tmura? Another obvious answer: תנא התם
משום תמורה, tana hatam mishum tmura, because there are two הלכות halachos
about a חטאת chatas that is מיתה. misa. One is no תמורה,
tmura, the other is no מעילה. me'ila. So it says it over
there for the purposes of תמורה. tmura. תנא הכא משום מעילה, tana
hacha mishum me'ila, it teaches it here for the purposes of מעילה.
me'ila. Okay, very straightforward גמרא. Gemara. Yes?
Maybe this is just an impression I'm getting, but I'm not sure
if it is correct, that if you have this חטאת, chatas, you
know, that like we talked about, that need—oh if you didn't bring
it, then you could have waited until it got a מום, mum,
is that ideal to do? Because because meanwhile, you're not having כפרה
kapara until it's—so like what should you do?
Should you—Yeah, that's a very interesting question. Yeah, I don't know. I
mean,
it sounds like yes. The משנה mishna says—the גמרא Gemara says תירעה
עד שתיסתאב ותימכר. teira'eh ad shetistave vetimacher. The משנה mishna seems to
be clearly telling you that.
משנה mishna says ואם עד שלא כיפרו הבעלים תירעה עד שתיסתאב. ve'im
ad shelo kiperu haba'alim teira'eh ad shetistave.
So, you know, yeah, but that means that you have a decision
to make right now. So that's exactly—which is better? It sounds like
that that's what's better. What's better is, if you have a decision
to make, here's what you should do: wait for it to get
a מום. mum.
And meanwhile you just don't have your כפרה. kapara.
Yeah, you're right. That's a good point.
That's what—and then the other question is, you know, about מעילה. me'ila.
But, you know, is there a rabbinic מעילה me'ila in this kind
of case?
So we're going to get to rabbinic מעילה. me'ila. For now, there's
a general question, which remember back in the beginning of the מסכת,
masechet, לא נהני lo neheni means rabbinically it's forbidden. Does it mean
that it's rabbinic מעילה meilah or not?
Either way it's אסור, assur, but like how אסור? assur? And one
certain נפקא מינה nafka mina would be that לא נהני lo neheni
if it's just an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, you don't give the
money back. If it's a rabbinic מעילה, meilah, there's no קרבן, korban,
there's no חומש, homesh, but at least you give back the money,
you know, towards some function. Even if it wasn't the stealing, even
if it was just the הנאה, hana'ah, but you at least you
pay money. So there is a big difference. So it's not always
clear whether לא נהני lo neheni just means an איסור דרבנן issur
derabbanan or even means a מעילה דרבנן. meilah derabbanan. For now, let's
assume it's an איסור דרבנן. issur derabbanan. We're going to get in
the next משניות mishnayot to cases of מעילה דרבנן. meilah derabbanan. Okay.
So you're saying this probably isn't מעילה?
meilah? At least based on the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, it
sounded like לא נהני lo neheni did not go so far to
say מעילה דרבנן. meilah derabbanan. Okay. By the way, in terms of
the principle here, just read the one short תוספות, tosafot, four lines
from the bottom on י"ב עמוד ב'. yod bet amud bet. לא
נהנין ולא מועלין, lo nehenin velo moalin, תוספות tosafot says דכיון דאזלי
לאיבוד לא שייכא בהו מעילה ולא קרינן בהו קדשי השם. dekeivan deazlei
le'ibbud lo shaicha behu meilah velo karinan behu kodshei Hashem. Since the
point is it has to get destroyed, let it die, that completely
takes it out of the category. But not just being פסול, pasul,
being פסול pasul as we said from the beginning of the מסכת,
masechet, it would still remain retain מעילה. meilah.
But it's interesting, המפרש hamefarash here says there is מעילה דרבנן. meilah
derabbanan.
I know, but I'm bracketing that for now. Okay, yes, it is
true, it's an open question what that means. Okay, so let's take
a look.
It's so tempting to save these animals, to do something.
Right, I know. Every time we get to חטאת המתה, chatat hametah,
you have to voice it.
It's some kind of torture.
Right, starve to death. Right.
But at least in עברה שנתה overa shenata so there is, they
said that you know, let it, that's one time, that's one thing.
When there's a possibility for getting a מום mum and redeeming it,
then yes, but if there isn't, then right and it's, yeah, I
know, it's very it's very troubling. It's true. Every time we get
to חטאת המתה, chatat hametah, it's the that's the... yeah, it doesn't
change from מסכת masechet to מסכת. masechet. It's good that you should
be here to voice the objection, to voice... it is a problem.
Okay, let's take a look at the next
משנה. mishnah. המפריש מעות לנזירותו. hamafrish ma'ot lineziruto. Now, somebody set aside
money, and he's a נזיר. nazir. Now a נזיר nazir has to
bring three קרבנות: korbanot: a חטאת, chatat, an עולה, olah, and a
שלמים. shelamim. He set aside a pile of money and said I'm
going to use this for my קרבנות. korbanot. Now I'm a נזיר,
nazir, when it's over I'm going to use it for my קרבנות.
korbanot. And he doesn't say which how he's going to divide it
for which קרבן. korban. לא נהנין, lo nehenin, you can't derive benefit
from this money. ולא מועלין, velo moalin, but if you did, it's
not מעילה. meilah. Why not? מפני שהן ראויין לבוא כולן שלמים. mipnei
shehen re'uyin lavo kullan shelamim.
Because it could have been used for part of it for an
עולה olah and a חטאת. chatat. Let's say you used all the
money. Well, okay, so the part at least there should be some
מעילה meilah because some of the money would have been an עולה
olah and a חטאת, chatat, and there's מעילה meilah by an עולה
olah and a חטאת, chatat, and therefore there's מעילה meilah by עולה
olah and חטאת chatat money. Ah, but no. You could say since
you didn't say, you could have used all of it for שלמים
shelamim and you could have bought עולה olah and חטאת chatat with
more money. So there and, as we know, by a שלמים shelamim
there's no מעילה meilah until זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, מעילה meilah applies
to the אימורין. immurin. So money set aside for a שלמים shelamim
there also is no מעילה. meilah. So although in theory some of
this could have been used for an עולה olah and חטאת chatat
and maybe that would have been the norm, but it's also in
theory possible it all could have been used for a שלמים, shelamim,
and therefore there is no clear מעילה meilah here.
But if he would have said this is to cover all my
קרבנות, korbanot, then there would be מעילה. meilah.
Right, I mean, I was expecting that you were going to ask.
If somebody explicitly said I am using this money for, I'm going
to buy, you know, from this money עולה, olah, שלמים, shelamim, and
חטאת. chatat. Right. And then presumably there would be מעילה meilah if
you use all the money, assuming you use all the money. Right,
exactly, yes.
On the other hand, you're not deriving benefit from a שלמים? shelamim?
You're not deriving benefit, what do you mean?
I mean, a שלמים shelamim is
yours and you're going to eat most of it.
Right. So that's the reason, because it's not קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim,
that's why a there's no מעילה meilah by a שלמים shelamim until
the זריקת הדם zrikat hadam and then there's מעילה meilah by the
אימורין. immurin. That's exactly the idea.
Fundamentally your שלמים shelamim is... Now we did point out by the
way, and it's worth repeating, that it's not just the practical question
of what you can use. There's also conceptually, does it start with
the idea that it's God's or start with the idea that it's
like... but even go there's דאמרינן קדשים קלים ממון בעלים, deamrinan kodashim
kalim mammon be'alim, it's certainly not as fully God's the same way
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is. So think, for example, the difference between
the meat of the חטאת chatat and the meat of the שלמים.
shelamim. Both of those are אסור assur to you before זריקת דם,
zrikat dam, right? And מותר mutar to you or to the כהנים
kohanim or whatever after זריקת דם. zrikat dam. Nevertheless, the meat of
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim there is מעילה meilah before זריקת דם zrikat
dam and the meat of קדשי קלים kodshei kalim there isn't. So
is this a larger conceptual issue, not just practically what can you
benefit from it, which says but conceptually קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is
fully God's and therefore until the meat becomes מותר mutar it's all
קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. קדשי קלים kodshei kalim is not fully God's
and therefore only until the אימורין immurin are designated and is זריקת
הדם zrikat hadam and only then do the אימורין immurin become מעילה.
meilah.
And that might apply even when the person bringing a חטאת chatat
is a כהן kohen and will be eating...
Absolutely, absolutely, but conceptually the חטאת chatat is... By the way, here's
an interesting way of thinking about it although it doesn't go all
the way, which is, you know, the eating of the כהנים, kohanim,
normally you say כהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים kohanim ochlim ube'alim mitkaprim and
it's seen as part of the bringing of the קרבן korban and
you say they're, you know, their eating is like משלחן גבוה. mishulchan
gavo'ah. Their, their eating is like the eating of the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
We say those things a lot less by the eating of the
owners for the שלמים. shelamim. So anyway, clearly your שלמים... shelamim... קדשי
קדשים Kodshei Kodashim is fundamentally a different category. Now, so that if
you had that pile of money, there's no מעילה me'ilah because it
could have all been used for a שלמים. Shlamim. מאי, mai, but
now this guy who was a נזיר nazir died, והיו לו מעות
סתומים, v'hayu lo ma'ot stumim, and you had just a pile he
had a pile of money, which he was going to use for
his for his נזיר nazir money, he didn't say what what is
what. So what do you do with that pile of money?
יפלו לנדבה, yipelu l'nedavah, it all gets used for an עולה. olah.
Okay, now why is that? Well,
basically, I mean the another גמרא Gemara says that it's like it's
just like הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe miSinai or something, but conceptually
also,
right, the he was a נזיר, nazir, you can't bring a חטאת
chatat because he's dead, you know, שלמים Shlamim is also sort of
probably distinctive to him having been a נזיר nazir and it's part
of the actual ritual of the ending of the נזירות. nezirut. עולה
olah is more like just סתם stam an עולה. olah. Even though
he was bringing it because he was a נזיר, nazir, there's nothing
that's distinctive about it. So it's also a reason to think why
this money now that he's dead should be used for an עולה.
olah.
So if he wasn't a נזיר nazir would it be any different?
Let's say he just had money and he set it aside for
a קרבן, korban, don't know which one it is, would it also
be an עולה? olah?
To set aside money for a generic קרבן korban and what you
didn't know if he meant an עולה olah or a שלמים? Shlamim?
I don't even know if you can It's an interesting question, can
you do that? What would the status of that money be?
I don't know. It's a good question. I don't know. Okay, so
it says like this.
Now, מעות מפורשים, ma'ot meforashim, let's say you have explicit pile the
guy had explicit piles of money, my חטאת chatat money, my עולה
olah money, my
אשם asham my שלמים Shlamim money. And then he dies.
מפורש meforash right?
Yeah, and you knew which was which. So what do you do
with the money? דמי חטאת יוליכו לים המלח, demei chatat yolichu l'Yam
HaMelach, so חטאת chatat money becomes almost like a חטאת שמתו בעליה,
chatat she'metu ba'aleha, so you throw it into the you destroy it.
At least here we're not doing it to an animal. לא נהנים,
lo nehenin, now what's the הלכה halacha status of that if you
before if you benefited from it? לא נהנים ולא מועלים, lo nehenin
v'lo mo'alin, there's no מעילה me'ilah just like last משנה Mishnah about
the actual חטאת chatat that was מתה, metah, this is just money
of חטאת המתה. chatat hametah. Okay. דמי עולה יביאו עולה, demei olah
yavi'u olah, the money for an עולה, olah, יביאו עולה, yavi'u olah,
that you bring an עולה. olah. Why not? Bring an you can
bring an עולה olah if somebody left over property sanctified עולה, olah,
you don't need the guy to be
alive. ומועלים בהן, u'mo'alin bahen, and therefore there is מעילה me'ilah for
עולה olah money. דמי שלמים, demei Shlamim, now the שלמים Shlamim money,
now even though he was sort of if you were alive it
would have been a distinctive נזיר שלמים, nazir Shlamim, since in principle
you can bring a if somebody left over money that he had
an animal he had sanctified as a שלמים, Shlamim, it could be
brought after his death. The only real thing you can't do that
for is a חטאת chatat and an אשם asham because it's about
his specific atonement. So even with this money you can bring a
שלמים, Shlamim, יביאו שלמים, yavi'u Shlamim, bring a שלמים, Shlamim, but because
it is a שלמים Shlamim of somebody who was sanctified as a
נזיר שלמים, nazir Shlamim, there's an interesting split הלכה. halacha. On the
one hand נאכלין ליום אחד, ne'echalin l'yom echad, you don't eat it
for two days, a normal שלמים Shlamim you eat for two days,
but שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir is only eaten for one day, so
it still has somewhat of that character. But ואין טעונים לחם, v'ein
te'unim lechem, you don't bring bread. The only you only bring bread
for a שלמים Shlamim of a נזיר, nazir, so it's quasi-שלמי נזיר,
shalmei nazir, one day, but not a full שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir
because you don't bring bread. And that is specifically because the, you
know, it said that you bring the bread על כפי הנזיר, al
kapei hanazir, on the hands of the נזיר nazir you bring the
bread. So the understanding is that the bread that comes with the
שלמים Shlamim is
specifically requires the presence of the נזיר nazir and it's specifically for
the נזירות nezirut ritual, the ending of the נזירות. nezirut. And without
the נזיר nazir and the ending of the נזירות, nezirut, you don't
have the bread. But the קדושה kedusha of the קרבן, korban, it
can still be a שלמים Shlamim and even without the נזיר, nazir,
enough of a שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir to limit it to one
day of eating. So it's a very interesting split case.
If I if it's a בריא bari and I'm bringing my שלמי
שמחה, shalmei simcha, can I use this or is it just a
separate thing?
It's sort of like we're trying to credit the guy who died.
No, we're not trying to credit the guy who died. We're just
trying to say that this קדושה, kedusha, what does it allow it
necessitates bringing the קרבן korban with money with this קדושה. kedusha. Are
we able to bring the קרבן korban when the guy's not around?
I mean your question has more to do about, you know, about
what types of things can you
obligations can you satisfy from things that are already sanctified, דמי חובה,
demei chovah, so it's a more complex question. But is your if
your question was just like does the status of שלמי נזיר shalmei
nazir prevent it having another status,
I mean let's say you're not talking about can I be יוצא,
yotzei, I'm trying to think about the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. I
don't know, I don't know. I have to think about it but
I have to look into it more actually. But the but the
basic point here is that no, we're not saying he's יוצא, yotzei,
we're just saying it's sanctified, are we able to bring it and
what's the status of a שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir that the נזיר
nazir isn't around for? It's still able to be brought, you don't
need him around like you do by a חטאת, chatat, but its
קדושה kedusha limits it to one day. Yes.
Is it no atonement after death is that why חטאת...
chatat... Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. מתיב ליה ריש לקיש, metiv lei Reish Lakish, וליתני נמי
המפריש מעות לקינים לא נהנים ולא מועלים, v'litni nami hamafrish ma'ot l'kinim
lo nehenin v'lo mo'alin, we are going to see in a משנה
Mishnah that an example where there's no מעילה me'ilah is if you
sanctify bird קרבנות korbanot and they're the wrong age. So there are
two types of bird קרבנות... korbanot... Torim u-venei yonah תורים ובני יונה,
Torim u-venei yonah, doves and pigeons or something like that. Anyway, I
wrote once a whole blog entry and looked it up exactly what
they were. But okay, let's call them now doves and pigeons. So
the thing is, one of them it says benei yonah בני יונה.
benei yonah. So benei yonah בני יונה benei yonah means that they
have to be young, tor תור tor has to be an adult.
So let's say you went ahead and you sanctified, this is going
to be a mishnah משנה mishnah coming up, for your korban קרבן
korban benei yonah בני יונה benei yonah that were adults or torim
תורים torim that were children. So you would say, okay, what's the
big deal? I mean, there should still be meilah מעילה. meilah. I
mean, okay, it's like it's got a mum מום, mum, right? So
you can't use it, but it should still be meilah מעילה. meilah.
If I sanctified a korban קרבן korban that had a mum מום,
mum, there would still be meilah מעילה. meilah. Or if I sanctified,
I don't know, a female korban קרבן korban for an olah עולה,
olah, there's still meilah מעילה meilah even though you can't use it.
Why by birds is there no meilah מעילה? meilah? So the gemara
גמרא gemara is going to say that here's the way in which
birds are different. There is no pidyon פדיון pidyon by birds. You
can never be transfer the kedushah קדושה kedushah by birds even if
it has a mum מום, mum, even if it's missing a limb.
Even though a bird, by birds mums מומים mumim don't matter, blemishes
don't matter, it never says tamim תמים, tamim, but missing a limb
does matter. And even so, there's no transferring of the kedushah קדושה.
kedushah. So if I sanctified a bird that's too old, it's basically
like the chata'at hamet חטאת המת. chata'at hamet. There is no way
this kedushah קדושה kedushah can be used. I can't bring the bird
and I can't transfer the kedushah קדושה. kedushah. So basically, it's like
the chata'at hamet חטאת המת, chata'at hamet, it's going le-ibud לאיבוד, le-ibud,
and therefore lo nehenin ve-lo mo'alin לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin
ve-lo mo'alin.
So you just have to kind of lock it up and not
feed it?
Yeah, that's not, presumably, although that's not spelled out, but presumably. I
mean, you could feed it, but then you have the hashash חשש
hashash about, you know, about, although the different, right. You know, actually,
that's a nice point which Rifka רבקה Rifka here here to increase
the, you know, the problem, is that once we said that a
chata'at hamet חטאת המת chata'at hamet there's no issur meilah איסור מעילה,
issur meilah, right, you could say, well, then it's not, you know,
the it's not the
why not keep it alive for its whole life because even if
you accidentally misuse it, it's not meilah מעילה, meilah, right? So the
consequence is not as great. So, I mean, it's not, you know,
the owner has to constantly be feeding an animal he's not getting
benefit out of, but actually does heighten the question, you know, the
objection of the idea that you have to let it die since
we're here learning here that even if you did misuse it, there
is no meilah מעילה. meilah.
Unless she becomes pregnant or?
Oh, that's a good point, right, right, right. So then it becomes
a vlad chata'at hamet ולד חטאת המת, vlad chata'at hamet, right, so
there are consequences you don't want to deal with, that's true. And
the owner and the owner and the owner, you know, wouldn't want
to feed an animal its whole life if he's not getting any
benefit out of it. But it is interesting that you don't you
wouldn't have the problem of meilah מעילה. meilah. Anyway, back to the
bird issue. So the birds, that's the story by birds. If the
bird is too old, can't be used, then there's not going to
be any no meilah מעילה meilah because there's nothing to be done
with it, it's basically holekh le-ibud הולך לאיבוד. holekh le-ibud. Now the
question is why is that true about if even if the bird
is too young? If the bird is too young, you wait until
it gets old. Okay, so we'll discuss that. But that let's take
a look now with that background, let's take a look at Reish
Lakish's ריש לקיש Reish Lakish question. Matkif lah Reish Lakish מתקיף לה
ריש לקיש, Matkif lah Reish Lakish, so Reish Lakish ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish asked, and
I'm back to the gemara גמרא, gemara, I'm beginning it. Okay, matkif
lah Reish Lakish מתקיף לה ריש לקיש, Matkif lah Reish Lakish, so
Reish Lakish ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asked, ve-lisni nami ha-mafrish ma'ot le-kinin
ולתני נמי המפריש מעות לקינין. ve-lisni nami ha-mafrish ma'ot le-kinin. Let's say
I put aside money for bird korbanot קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, ve-lo nehenin
ve-lo mo'alin
ולא נהנין ולא מועלין, ve-lo nehenin ve-lo mo'alin, why don't we say
there's no even if it's what's a normal bird korban קרבן korban
is usually olah ve-chata'at עולה וחטאת. olah ve-chata'at. So why don't we
say there's no issur meilah איסור מעילה? issur meilah? Why not? I
mean, if I have to use it for an olah ve-chata'at עולה
וחטאת, olah ve-chata'at, it's definitely going to be, you know, meilah מעילה.
meilah. So why why is he arguing there should be no meilah
מעילה? meilah? For the following reason. Bi-pnei she-ein re'uyin le-havi torim she-lo
higia zemanam u-venei yonah she-avar zemanam מפני שאין ראוין להביא תורים שלא
הגיע זמנם ובני יונה שעבר זמנם. bi-pnei she-ein re'uyin le-havi torim she-lo
higia zemanam u-venei yonah she-avar zemanam. Because maybe I'll use the money
for a too young of a tor תור tor or too old
of a benei yonah בני יונה. benei yonah. And therefore there won't
be meilah מעילה meilah if I use it that way. Now of
course phrased that way it's like a crazy question. There's no meilah
מעילה meilah because I could use it for something wrong that I
shouldn't use it for? But I mean what I'm supposed to use
it for obviously there is meilah מעילה. meilah. So Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
reframes the question. He says no, he really doesn't mean both. He
really means I could use it for a tor תור tor that's
too young. And if I use it for a tor תור tor
that's too young, that actually could work. Then I would buy the
tor תור, tor, I couldn't use it now, there would be no
meilah מעילה meilah now, but I'd wait a few months and then
I could use it. So I actually wouldn't do anything wrong by
buying a too young tor תור, tor, I would just have to
wait. But if I did that, then at the moment of purchase,
at least initially, there would be no meilah מעילה. meilah. Well, because
there's no meilah מעילה meilah when the bird is too young. So
he says why don't we say there's no meilah מעילה meilah now
also? Maybe I'll use it for that type of a korban קרבן.
korban. At least that'll be my initial purchase and there won't be
meilah מעילה. meilah. So that's at least a better question than I
could use it for the wrong thing. I could use it for
the right thing, it's just not right it's just not immediately right
and there wouldn't be meilah מעילה. meilah.
And then he used benei yonah
she-avar zemanam בני יונה שעבר זמנם. benei yonah she-avar zemanam. Yeah, he
says lav davka לאו דוקא. lav davka. His real question was about
the tor she-lo higia zemano תור שלא הגיע זמנו. tor she-lo higia
zemano. Okay, it makes the question a lot better. So let's see
what the answer is. Amar Rava אמר רבא, Amar Rava, Amra Torah
bi-mostumim havei shelamim אמרה תורה במותר סתומים יהא שלמים. Amra Torah bi-mostumim
havei shelamim. Because he says give me a break. The you know,
there's still an ideal way and a proper way you're supposed to
do it. So by the nazir נזיר nazir money, the Torah is
totally okay if you buy a shelamim שלמים shelamim with the nazir
נזיר nazir money even if you use all the money to buy
shelamim שלמים. shelamim. Amra Torah hada אמרה תורה חדא. Amra Torah hada.
הגיע זמנם? higiah zmanan?
Do you think the תורה Torah is telling you buy birds that
are too young, שאינם ראויים למזבח, she'einam reuyim l'mizbeach, that right now
are not fit? Notice he only mentions the too young case. So
it's funny, one case it's a statement, the second half of the
statement it's a question mark, it's a bit תמיה, tmiah, not exactly
clear, but that's how you have to read it. So Rava says
look, I get it that in theory you could buy too young
birds and wait and then use them later. Okay, but that's not
what you're supposed to do with the money. You're supposed to do
with, buy it, if you're going to use the money, buy something
that could be used now. So if you put aside the money
for the birds, we're assuming that the status of that money is
to buy a קרבן korban that will be valid right away, and
there will be מעילה, me'ilah, and because that's where that money is
designated, the money itself, which has that קדושה, kedushah, there also is
מעילה me'ilah by that money.
Yes, the same should apply to another קרבן korban when you could
not buy a two-day-old lamb, for example.
Oh, you mean because it's מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman. Right. Okay, but
the only difference is that there is מעילה me'ilah by מחוסר זמן,
mechusar zman, there is not מעילה me'ilah by two young birds. So
we have to know why. We'll get to that. We're getting to
the משנה mishna about the young birds. I just gave you the
background. Why there's no מעילה me'ilah by the old birds, that's clear,
because there's no פדיון הולך לאיבוד. pidyon holech l'ibud. Too young, we're
taking it for granted, we will examine it in a minute. Okay,
but it's a good point, right. You could have מחוסר זמן mechusar
zman instead of, the fact that it can't be used right now
doesn't mean there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Birds is a unique case. Okay,
let's take a look now at the next. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi
Shimon omer: הדם קל בתחילה וחמור בסופו. hadam kal b'tchila v'chamur b'sofo.
Now we're talking about not the animals, but the parts of the
animals, as it were, once it's shachted. We've been talking about מעילה
me'ilah by the meat and the אימורין. imurin. What about the blood?
So he says the blood actually is more lenient at the beginning
and more strict at the end. Okay, הנסכים, hansachim, and when it
comes to the נסכים, nesachim, the wines that's poured with the
קרבן, korban, חומר בתחילתן וקל בסופן chomer b'tchilatan v'kal b'sofan and easier
at the end. Let's take a look. דם בתחילתו אין מועלין
בו. dam b'tchilato ein moalin bo. Initially, there's no מעילה me'ilah by
blood, which is bizarre, right? I mean, if anything is כולו להשם,
kulo l'Hashem, it's the blood. So what does it mean there's no
מעילה me'ilah by the blood? Okay, number one, we'll see that in
the גמרא, Gemara, but that's a shocker. יצא לנחל קדרון, yatza l'nachal
Kidron, now it goes out to the Kidron Wadi, which basically is
what they said, that all the blood that they had on the
floor of the מזבח, mizbeach, they washed it out, you know, the
first instances of the squeegees and the holes in the floor they
had in the מקדש, Mikdash, they washed it all out into a
funnel, and the, you know, and the funnel took it out into
the, into the Kidron Valley, and they sold it to farmers as
fertilizer. Okay, and there was
a, there was like a, a stream,
a stream or a pipe, yeah, thank you, that was a channel,
exactly. Okay, so there we say that we say that until it's
sold to farmers, if they want to use that blood without buying
for it and without transferring the קדושה kedushah etc., then it would
be, there would be מעילה. me'ilah. So מועלין בו, moalin bo, there
is מעילה. me'ilah. Now the thing to point out about this, which
is actually not explicit in the גמרא Gemara but is clear from
other sources, is that even when we say there's מעילה me'ilah by
this blood after it's in the Kidron Valley, that's only דרבנן drabbanan
מעילה. me'ilah. And here, even though it uses מועלין, moalin, but it
means דרבנן drabbanan מעילה me'ilah because, first of all,
well, the basic reason is it's נעשית מצוותו. na'asait mitzvato. You know,
once the דם dam was put on the מזבח, mizbeach, נעשית מצוותו,
na'asait mitzvato, and the גמרא Gemara says, you know, אין לך דבר
שנעשית מצוותו שמועלין בו. ein l'cha davar she'na'asait mitzvato she'moalin bo. If
it's a קרבן, korban, once it's done, it's done, and there's no
מעילה me'ilah once it's נעשית מצוותו. na'asait mitzvato. So here it's דרבנן
drabbanan מעילה me'ilah after it's done. But the interesting thing is, beforehand,
no מעילה me'ilah at all, not even דרבנן. drabbanan. Afterwards, and there's
going to actually be מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, admittedly דרבנן, drabbanan, but afterwards
there's מעילה. me'ilah. So that's very ironic, that's by the blood. And
we don't even know why beforehand not. נסכים, nesachim, the wine, בתחילתן
מועלין בהן, b'tchilatan moalin bahen,
initially the wine is sanctified for a קרבן, korban, so of course,
you know, to be poured, so of course there's מעילה. me'ilah. ירדו
לשיתין, yardu l'shisin,
they go down into the, into the funnels and into the, into
the sort of caverns. We'll talk about what שיתין shisin means in
a minute. But once the wine is poured, you know, down the
funnels in the, in
the altar, אין מועלין בהן, ein moalin bahen, there's no מעילה. me'ilah.
Now that's obvious, even דרבנן. drabbanan. But that's obviously נעשית מצוותו. na'asait
mitzvato. Okay, so there still might be לא נהנין, lo nehenin, there's
always the question is, is there לא נהנין? lo nehenin? But there's
certainly not מועלין. moalin. So again, why compare the wine to the
דם, dam, why not compare it to the meat or whatever? But
there is a comparison. First of all, they're both liquids that go
on the מזבח. mizbeach. And they're both things that we're not exactly
told what to do with them after. The meat is eaten, or
it's burned. The אימורין imurin are burned. So there, you know, it's
sort of clear. You can't eat the blood. Right. Well, right. You
could use it, you know, you could use it for, but anyway,
there we know what's done. The wine, what do you do with
it after? The blood, what do you do with it after? So
there and so therefore there's this comparison being made. But the wine
is the standard הלכה. halacha. There's
מעילה, me'ilah, נעשית מצוותו, na'asait mitzvato, no מעילה. me'ilah. The blood is
really the curious one. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: מועלין בדמים, moalin b'damim, דברי רבי מאיר.
divrei Rabbi Meir. There is מעילה me'ilah by blood. That's what Rabbi
Meir says. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Shimon. וחכמים
אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, אין מועלין, ein moalin, you
don't, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר אין מועלין? mai
ta'ama d'man d'amar ein moalin? What's the reason?
אמר עולא אמר קרא, Amar Ula amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says:
and I've given it to you for you on the altar to
atone. לכם *Lachem*, שלכם *shelachem* too, it's yours, so it's doing a
service to you, and that somehow takes it out of קדשי השם
Hashem. *Kodshei Hashem*. Again, so ironic, I don't even really know how
to begin to sort of get my head around this idea. The
whole point is that it all is to God and it's you're
giving the soul of the animal to God and so on. But
here it says, oh, but it's doing a service for you. That
takes it out of the full concept of קדשי השם *Kodshei Hashem*
and there's no מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא *Dvei Rabi
Yishmael tana*: לכפר *L'chaper*. לכפרה נתתיו ולא למעילה *L'chaparah netativ v'lo l'me'ilah*,
which is I want, which is at least there you're sort of,
you know, it's a little clearer the point, you know, conceptually what
it's about. It's there to help you. So, you know, the whole
point of this is to allow you to get atonement and it's
not to cause you to stumble up. It's not to it's not
to bring about sin. So therefore this blood I've completely exempted it,
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is saying from מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah* the way
חז"ל *Chazal* are reading it because it's here to help you, it's
here to atone for you.
Why wouldn't you say that
about the whole
קרבן *korban*? I know. Right.
Why are they saying?
Exactly. Say all these things are here to help you. Right. I
know and that's what I really don't know what to say. You
know.
Especially a חטאת *chatat*.
Right, right, right.
So that they wouldn't have to die. Right, exactly.
רבי יוחנן אמר אמר קרא *Rabi Yochanan amar amar kra*, the פסוק
*pasuk* says, כי הדם הוא hu. בנפש יכפר *ki hadam hu banefesh
yichaper*, because the soul is the blood or the blood is in
the soul and through that you will be atoned. That's it. So
הדם הוא *hadam hu* is the soul. Yes. Why does that help
us?
The whole animal isn't it just? I know.
But let's see what he does with the דרשה *drasha*. How does
that explain why there's no
מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*? It says,
לפני כפרה כלאחר כפרה *lifnei chaparah k'le'achar chaparah*. הדם הוא *Hadam hu*
meaning it is the blood, one status for the blood and through
which you achieve atonement. So לפני כפרה כלאחר כפרה *lifnei chaparah k'le'achar
chaparah*. הוא *Hu*. מה לאחר כפרה
אין בו מעילה Me'ilah *Ma l'achar
chaparah ein bo me'ilah*? The same way after atonement there shouldn't be
מעילה Me'ilah? *me'ilah* because it's נעשית מצוותו *na'aseit mitzvato*, right? You don't
normally once something is נעשית מצוותו *na'aseit mitzvato* there's no מעילה Me'ilah
*me'ilah*. Again, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says there is מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*
but that's rabbinic. Okay, that's funny. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't exactly
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* takes it for granted that's rabbinic. After
זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* there's no מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah*. That's נעשית מצוותו
*na'aseit mitzvato*. So אף לפני כפרה אין בו מעילה me'ilah *af lifnei
chaparah ein bo me'ilah* so the same applies even before because it
has one status. Of course, as opposed to everything else which statuses
change, this has one status based on the פסוק *pasuk*. ואימא *V'eima*,
why don't I say מה לפני כפרה יש בו מעילה me'ilah אף
לאחר כפרה יש בו מעילה me'ilah. *ma lifnei chaparah yesh bo me'ilah
af l'achar chaparah yesh bo me'ilah*? How do you know which way
to go? Why don't I say beforehand there is מעילה me'ilah, *me'ilah*
like everything that's sanctified and therefore afterwards there is מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah*?
חסא *Chasa*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. וכי יש לך דבר
שנעשית מצוותו ויש בו מעילה v'yeish bo me'ilah. *V'chi yesh lacha davar
she'na'aseit mitzvato v'yesh bo me'ilah*? That would violate we have a clear
principle that once it's נעשית מצוותו *na'aseit mitzvato* מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* can't
apply. So if we have to interpret the פסוק *pasuk* anyway, we'll
talk about an exemption of מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* beforehand rather than מעילה
me'ilah *me'ilah* after. How do we know that though? What's the? Well,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to challenge it. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says I mean it's true how we know that more has
to do with just a, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* works
with that logical assumption. It actually doesn't even learn it from a
פסוק *pasuk*. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s actually going to challenge
it that there are exceptions to the rule.
What is נעשית מצוותו *na'aseit mitzvato*?
The mitzvah's done. Meaning in the קרבן *korban* once what you did
with it what you were supposed, it's done and it's out of
the category. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמאי לא אמאי לא
*amai lo amai lo*. Is it really true that nothing else nothing
that once the mitzvah is done there's no מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*? הרי
תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen *Harei trumat hadeshen*. How about תרומת הדשן trumat
hadeshen. *trumat hadeshen* again? שנעשית מצוותו ויש בו מעילה me'ilah *She'na'aseit mitzvato
v'yesh bo me'ilah*. The mitzvah's done and there is מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*.
Now don't confuse this with the discussion a day or two ago
about is there מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* after תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen, *trumat
hadeshen*. That was is there מעילה meila *me'ilah* in the ashes
after תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen, *trumat hadeshen* was done? Is there anything
are the ashes still is there a mitzvah left to be done
in the terms of taking them out of the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash*
or once the תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen* was done the ashes are
no longer have any mitzvah and there's no מעילה meila *me'ilah* in
the ashes. Here the question is the ashes used in the תרומת
הדשן *trumat hadeshen* itself. So the כהן kohen, *Kohen* takes the תרומת
הדשן *trumat hadeshen* a scoop of ashes from the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*,
walks down right the the ramp, puts them at the side of
the ramp. That's the mitzvah of תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*, the ritual
done every day. Those ashes there still is מעילה meila? *me'ilah*. Now
why? If anything you would say that's a classic נעשית מצוותו *na'aseit
mitzvato*. You're done, you took them, you put it down, you're done,
end of story. So we're going to learn from a פסוק *pasuk*
that מעילה meila *me'ilah* continues to apply to those ashes, not the
stuff on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*, but those ashes to which the
תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen* was done. Okay?
So he takes it out to the בית הדשן *beit hadeshen*?
No, you don't do anything with it. The reason the reason
we're going to learn that מעילה *me'ilah* applies is the פסוק *pasuk*
says והניחם שם ve-hinicham sham, *v'henicham sham* or והניחו שם *v'henicho sham*
and he places it there and we say there means it has
to remain there, it can't be used for anything else. According to
חז"ל *Chazal* כהנא בבגדי כהונה איני *kahana b'vigdei kehuna eini*?
Oh that's another פסוק *pasuk*.
So what does it say by the תרומת הדשן *trumat hadeshen*? So
it says ושמו vesamo, אצל המזבח etzel ha-mizbe'ach. *v'samo eitzel hamizbeach*. So
somehow we're learning from, I don't know, we'll see, but anyway somehow
we learn ושמו אצל המזבח *v'samo eitzel hamizbeach* that it remains אצל
המזבח *eitzel hamizbeach*, it doesn't move. and therefore they understand that it
even gets absorbed into the ground, but the point sort of says
is it has to preserve its state and they learn from the
idea of preserving its state means that מעילה continues. Now that, you
know, why would we say that? Maybe it just stays there, you
know, even even though it's stopped מעילה, but somehow we wouldn't be
מקפיד makpid on, you know, retaining a state unless it retained also
its status of קדושה. kedusha. So they understand that once the ashes
are put there, you don't move them and מעילה continues even though
the
מצוה'ס mitzvah's done.
And when we had the discussion before it was about everything that
was left behind, are there still מצות mitzvot to do there in
terms of removing it? But here we say the idea is that
there's an idea of it remaining and therefore its status continues. So
there's a case of נעשית מצותו, na'aseit mitzvato, okay, ויש בו מעילה.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, משום דהוי תרומת הדשן ואיברי שעיר
משתלח שני כתובים הבאים כאחד mishum d'havei trumat hadeshen v'evarim se'ir mishtale'ach
shnei ketuvim habaim k'echad
because
the best answer to there's an exception is ah, but there are
two exceptions. Okay, so because there's another exception then therefore those don't
become the rule, they become the exception. What's the other exception? So
when you send the שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir La'azazel, right, and you throw
it over the cliff, so therefore that has קדושה kedusha and we
learn out that even after it goes over the cliff and it
becomes shattered that the limbs, we don't say נעשית מצותו na'aseit mitzvato
and now there's no מעילה, the limbs remain קדושה kedusha and מעילה
and אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and so on. So there again is
another exception to the rule and we have two exceptions, therefore we
do not generalize them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says כל שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. kol shnei ketuvim habaim k'echad ein melamdim.
Two exceptions, we would not generalize. So yeah, there are exceptions but
they are limited, it's only those. So the גמרא Gemara says הני
ניחא למאן דאמר איברי שעיר המשתלח אין נהנין מהם. hani nicha leman
de'amar evarei se'ir hamishtale'ach ein nehenin mehem. That's good if you're of
the opinion that says that you learn out that the איסור issur
still applies even after they go over the cliff. Okay, now this
little interesting phrase is אין נהנין. ein nehenin. The question is does
the איסור issur that still applies an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah or
is it actually an איסור issur of מעילה? But anyway, for now
we'll bracket that. As long as you say that, there's what to
talk about, that that's a similar case. אלא למאן דאמר נהנין מהם,
Ela leman de'amar nehenin mehem, but there's an opinion that says that
what, it's נעשית מצותו na'aseit mitzvato and you can derive benefit from
the limbs of the שעיר se'ir after it gets pushed off the
cliff. So you only have one exception and one exception should become
a rule, right? If there's only one exception, we normally would say
let's turn it into the rule. So מאי איכא למימר, mai ika
lemeimar, what can you say? The גמרא Gemara says no, there's another
exception. משום דהוי תרומת הדשן ובגדי כהונה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. mishum
d'havei trumat hadeshen u'vigdei kehuna shnei ketuvim habaim k'echad.
There's another exception, not just תרומת הדשן but something else that gets
placed by the מזבח, mizbe'ach which is the clothes of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And there we learn
by the פסוק of והניחם שם, you place them there, which somehow
we learn is leave them there and they can't be used for
anything else and מעילה continues to apply even though you're done and
it's not going to be used for anything else. וכל שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. v'chol shnei ketuvim habaim k'echad ein melamdim. And
therefore you can't apply it. So those remain exceptions. Are there exceptions?
Yes, but there's two exceptions and we don't apply them.
And if there's three exceptions then certainly those are the exception.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara says exactly, הני ניחא לרבנן. hani nicha
lerabbanan. That's good according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. דאמרי והניחם שם מלמד
שטעונים גניזה, de'amri ve-hinicham sham melamed she'te'unim geniza, that they have to
be buried, they can't be used for anything else, so they retain
also their status and they retain an איסור מעילה. issur Me'ilah. שפיר,
Shappir, it's good.
אלא רבי דוסא Ela Rabbi Dosa דאמר מותר להשתמש בהן כהן הדיוט.
de'amar mutar le-hishtamesh bahen kohen hedyot. רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa says somewhat
ironically that all the הלכה halacha of בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna is
just that it can't be used for another יום כיפור אחר, Yom
Kippur acher, but another כהן, kohen not a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
could use it during the year. So according to him, you don't
have that whole example.
Can it be used for another, if it can't be used another
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, then even a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can
use it, right?
During, yeah, so that's the question. Can it be used, it can't
be used for יום כיפור אחר, Yom Kippur acher, can it be
used for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for his בגדי לבן bigdei
lavan during the year? Maybe. Normally the phrase in the גמרא Gemara
is, you know, מותר להשתמש בהן כהן הדיוט. mutar le-hishtamesh bahen kohen
hedyot. Okay, but the emphasis is, but you're right, the emphasis is
don't use it on another יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, anyway,
so according to him,
מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, what can you say? There's still
only one exception.
And he holds from the other one.
And presumably, it's possible that he also would say you can benefit
from the שעיר המשתלח. se'ir hamishtale'ach. So we still have only one
exception of the תרומת הדשן. So it says משום דהוי תרומת הדשן
ועגלה ערופה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. mishum d'havei trumat hadeshen ve-egla arufa
shnei ketuvim habaim k'echad. Ah, there's another thing that even after you're
done remains forbidden, the עגלה ערופה. egla arufa. Okay, you break the
neck and we learn from other places that it remains אסור assur
and therefore it's an exception. Of course, the problem is is that
עגלה ערופה egla arufa is no longer about מעילה, right? עגלה ערופה
egla arufa is not sanctified. So עגלה ערופה egla arufa might become
אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and נעשית מצותו, na'aseit mitzvato, so in a
way these are telling us a principle that sometimes נעשית מצותו na'aseit
mitzvato doesn't change the status. But it's not exactly telling us the
idea that מעילה continues if we're bringing in עגלה ערופה. egla arufa.
What it tells us the idea is there are cases where נעשית
מצותו na'aseit mitzvato does not lead to a status change. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says הני ניחא למאן דאמר אין מלמדין. hani nicha
leman de'amar ein melamdim. Fine, now you've got two, which nobody debates.
But that's only good if you say that you can't learn out
from two. אלא למאן דאמר מלמדין, Ela leman de'amar melamdim, according to
the opinion that even if you have two exceptions you can apply
them more generally and they become the rule, מאי איכא למימר, mai
ika lemeimar, what can you say? What can you say? תרי מיעוטי
כתיבי. trei mi'utei ketivi. No, there are other things that say only
these cases. כתיב התם ketiv hatam הערופה, ha-arufah, the ערופה. arufah. So
the status what applies here don't apply elsewhere, here the status applies
after נעשה מצוותו, na'aseh mitzvato, not elsewhere. וכתיב התם ve-ketiv hasam it
says by the תרומת הדשן, ושמו, place it, only it, אצל המזבח.
הני אין, hani in, here's cases where the status applies after נעשה
מצוותו, na'aseh mitzvato, מדי אחריני לא, mi-di achrini lo, other places not.
Now I want to take a step back and point out that
the גמרא Gemara really at some level didn't answer the question because
the question was how do we know that דם dam is אסור
assur is מותר muttar beforehand? Because we compare before and after. So
the same way after it's מותר muttar certainly going to be מותר
muttar before. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says one minute, maybe both before
and after it's אסור. assur. It says no no no no no,
everything is always מותר muttar after נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato it's always
מותר. muttar. Okay and then it went through the whole thing that
there are exceptions but you can't use the exceptions to prove the
rule. Now the problem is we're not asking to prove the rule,
we can grant that the general rule is that after נעשה מצוותו
na'aseh mitzvato it becomes מותר, muttar, but what we're saying is there
are some exceptions, right? There's תרומת הדשן, there's maybe עגלה ערופה, Eglah
Arufah, there are some exceptions. So all we were saying was not
let's make the rule that נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato doesn't matter but
let's just say דם dam is an exception. So you can't tell
me there are no exceptions, there are exceptions. So getting into the
whole discussion about כי שני כתובים אין מלמדין ki shnei kesuvim ein
melamdin da da da all that says is that you can't make
a rule out of the exceptions. Okay but our question was who
tells us that דם dam also isn't an exception.
Unless you know it's an exception you assume it's part of the
rule.
Yeah, but then yeah, maybe, but that, you know, that it was
a little, it was a little not a real direct answer because
the question is how come it can't be an exception? It says
oh there are never any exceptions. Ah there are exceptions. Okay but
those aren't the rule. We're not saying it should be the rule
we're just saying let it be an exception. Anyway, so that's what
the גמרא has. And it is interesting also to note the shift
that the idea of נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato is not just a
מעילה concept because when we're trying to prove exceptions to this rule
we didn't limit ourselves to מעילה cases. We went to עגלה ערופה
Eglah Arufah where there's no מעילה. So it's a more general concept
of status changes whatever that status is after נעשה מצוותו. na'aseh mitzvato.
By the way another classic example we normally have is by איסור
הנאה issur hana'ah which we're now from מעילה, like if there's a
מצווה mitzvah of שריפה sereifah of your חמץ chametz after you burn
it it's מותר בהנאה. muttar be-hana'ah. Okay so these are it's a
more general concept that נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato changes the status and
therefore we brought cases that weren't just מעילה. But we're back to
our general point though that דם dam for some reason ironically דם
dam is something that there is no מעילה for from the get-go
even though we would have said it's כולו לה' kulo la-Hashem and
when it says in the משנה Mishna there is מעילה after it's
done after נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato washes it out, that's only מעילה
דרבנן. me'ilah de-rabbanan. Okay no interestingly the גמרא just jumps over that
even though that obviously is crying for explanation because we just got
through a whole thing of נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato but there presumably
because that was just so common I mean every day there would
be tons of דם, dam, they would have to get it out
of the מקדש, right? And people would want to use it as
fertilizer so presumably we learned at the beginning of the מסכת masekhet
that certain issues that were שכיח shchiach and so on you know
they want to make a מעילה דרבנן me'ilah de-rabbanan that's just a
speculation but it's interesting because exactly exactly exactly but that's why but
it it's interesting that the גמרא skips over that, yes.
We שחט shecht an animal, we can't eat the דם. dam. Right,
but we benefit from it. Right, so this is another... Yeah, yeah.
The איסור issur here of מעילה דרבנן me'ilah de-rabbanan is not because
it's דם dam and דם dam can't be eaten, it's because it's
קדשים, kodshim, you know, and so right, so yeah, yeah.
What'd you say if you burn the חמץ chametz you can it's
useful?
You can use the- yeah you can use the ashes. Exactly. Right.
And that's a general concept that נעשה מצוותו na'aseh mitzvato changes status
and here we did that by comparing and I should also say
by the way תוספות Tosafot points out that even though the גמרא
quoted a ברייתא baraita whether there's מעילה by דם dam
and other גמרות Gemarot other considerations whatever says even the opinions here
that says there is מעילה by דם dam only means מעילה דרבנן
me'ilah de-rabbanan like
the מעילה that applies after it washes out that everybody really agrees
to the principle that דאורייתא de-Oraita there's no מעילה by דם dam
and a very shocking but that ironically is the הלכה. halakhah. Just
quickly how does that work? If it's sold to the farmers so
some farmer wants to use it they have to go to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and pay them?
No no we have a pipe through which all the bloody whatever
water comes out. Some were collecting it in I don't know gallon
tubs here somewhere out you know wherever the pipe leads and then
I sell it to farmers and if you give
me- the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash sells
it to farmers and the money they pay goes to the- goes
to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. The קדושה, kedushah, the rabbinic קדושה
kedushah of the דם dam transfers to the money and they get
the דם dam and they use it to fertilize.
So me as the farmer I can't just like you know scoop
it up myself and then bring it to my field. I have
to buy it from the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Right exactly exactly and that's what it means that there's
an איסור מעילה דרבנן. issur me'ilah de-rabbanan. Right. Okay.
So it would be מעילה if the farmer took it.
Yes, rabbinic. מעילה correct. Okay so now it goes on.
Now נסכים בתחילה מועלין בהם.
nesachim bitchila moalin bahem. So there is מעילה by the נסכים nesachim
by the wine but not after they've been poured like any normal
thing that's finished its מצוה mitzvah so for the מזבח. mizbe'ach So
the גמרא says like this לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק.
leima matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Tzadok. Let's say our משנה Mishna
is not like רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Tzadok. דתניא
רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר לול קטן היה בין כבש למזבח שבמערבו
של כבש. detanya Rabbi Elazar berabi Tzadok omer lul katan haya bein
keves lamizbe'ach shebema'aravo shel keves. There was a little
trapdoor essentially
between the ramp and the altar because there was a little gap
between where the ramp ended.
Just like a hair's breadth.
All right it was a tiny whatever but תוספות Tosefot says I
think probably between where the מזבח mizbe'ach.
goes beyond the ramp. It's not literally between.
Okay the word לול? lul?
לול lul can mean like a something we talk about a לול
של תרנגולים lul shel tarnagolim it could mean like a coop. A
coop but here basically you'll see what it's going to describe. So
it'll describe essentially like a chicken coop but laid lengthwise. So basically
what it's going to talk about is that let's imagine this is
look this is very easy you don't need a picture. This is
your ramp this is your altar. Okay they would go ahead and
they would pour the wine down little funnels at the top of
the מזבח mizbe'ach like right here they'd pour the wine. Now according
to where would that wine go? So then there would be funnels
would bring it into the hollow of the מזבח. mizbe'ach It says
שיתין. shitin. What are the שיתין? shitin? So there's actually a מחלוקת
machloket in the גמרא in סוכות Sukkot where it goes. Some say
basically the whole hollow of the מזבח mizbe'ach. it would just go
into the hollow of the מזבח mizbe'ach and it would over the
years get filled with a lot of wine which would eventually dry
up and sort of clots of wine. Others say that it would
actually keep on going deep into the ground. Okay. So if the
hollow is getting filled up with clots of wine where are how
are you ever cleaning it out? So here we're saying there's a
little trapdoor okay down here at the base maybe not literally between
maybe just where it extends at the base right near. And the
כהן goes into the trapdoor he gets into the hollow of the
מזבח. It's like what do they call those things
when there are like up the
ducts? Thank you. You know they've got those ducts or whatever so
that you can climb to get access between. So that's basically what
it is right he's got that tunnel that duct goes in and
then he just whatever he cleans out all of the gooky wine
and then there's the question can you use that wine or not?
Is there מעילה? Well that's our משנה Mishna אין מועלין ein moalin
afterwards. Okay. So let's take a look. He says like this so
he says so that's what לול lul here means. It's like a
duct okay it's like a sideways chicken coop. לול קטן היה בין
כבש למזבח שבמערבו של כבש. lul katan haya bein keves lamizbe'ach shebema'aravo
shel keves. It was at the west of the ramp which is
I mean it's a little bit funny west of the ramp because
the ramp ends at its west so everything if it's between the
כבש keves and the מזבח it's obviously at the west of the
ramp right? This is east this is west anyway. All right anyway
once every seventy years פרחי כהונה pirchei kehuna little small כהנים kohanim
boys probably kids is what that means. They were small they could
fit into this little duct יורדין לו yordin lo go down into
it ומביאין יין קרוש umeivi'in yayin karush and they bring out the
congealed wine שהוא דומה לעיגולי דבילה shehu domeh l'igulei dvela which is
like these rounds of pressed up pressed dates right? It's dates or
figs? Figs figs. ושורפין אותו בקדושה vesorfin oto bikdusha and they burn
it in a holy place right they do like what you do
like פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim you burn it שנאמר בקדש הסך נסך
שכר להשם. shenemar bakodesh hasech nesech shechar l'Hashem. In this is talking
about the pouring of the נסכים nesachim in the holy place you
shall pour it a pouring of intoxicating liquid to השם. כשם שניסוכה
בקדושה שריפתה בקדושה. keshem shenisucha bikdusha srefata bikdusha. The same way the
pouring is בקדושה bikdusha the burning is בקדושה. bikdusha. Probably by the
double language of הסך נסך hasech nesech they're saying that you always
do it it always remains בקדושה. bikdusha. מאי משמע? mai mashma? So
where do you get it? ואמר רבינא אתיא קדש קדש. ve'amar Ravina
atya kodesh kodesh. So he says it's not הסך נסך hasech nesech
it's a גזירה שוה gezeira shava of קדש קדש. kodesh kodesh. כתיב
הכא בקדש ksiv hacha bakodesh וכתיב התם ושרפת את הנותר באש לא
יאכל כי קדש הוא. vechesiv hatam vesarafta et hanosar ba'esh lo ye'achel
ki kodesh hu. I think it's הוא. Okay so there talks about
it says קדש kodesh and it talks about burning it because of
its קדושה. kedusha. ומה נותר שריפתו בקדושה אף האי נמי בקדושה. umah
notar srefato bikdusha af hai nami bikdusha. So in general we learn
out from נותר notar that any פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim there's a
מצות שריפה mitzvat srefa and in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay
this isn't exactly פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim but it's stuff that the
מצוה mitzvah has been done with so therefore you burn it. Now
the גמרא starts by saying our משנה Mishna is not like רבי
אלעזר ברבי צדוק. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Tzadok. Why not? Because the גמרא
says of course not why isn't it רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק? Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Tzadok? Because he says that you have to burn it
and our משנה says there's no מעילה but okay so right your
assumption being that if you have to burn it that means that
it. still retains its קדושה *kedushah* and therefore there should still be
מעילה *me'ilah*. Okay, and sell to farmers. Right. Okay, so anyway let's
see what the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
אפילו תימא רבי אליעזר בר צדוק *afilu tema Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok*.
No, it could be him. דאיקלט *de-iklat* or דאיקרט *de-ikrat* you caught
it. Now what does that mean? So תוספות *Tosafot* says what it
means would be the reason it why does it have its its
קדושה *kedushah*? Isn't it נעשית מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato*? So תוספות *Tosafot* says
no, no, no, because if it's going into the חלל *challal* of
the מזבח *Mizbe'ach* and it hits the floor of the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*,
that now, the same way that we say the floor of the
בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* is מקדש *mekadesh*, that now gives it a
certain level of קדושה *kedushah*. Okay, at least דרבנן *de-rabbanan*. Anyway, so
the scenario we're saying that there's no מעילה *me'ilah* would be that
you were inside the חלל *challal* and you caught it before it
hit the floor. That's at least the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer at this
stage. We'll see in a second there's another answer. So, you're right,
the fact that you burn it בקדושה *b'kedushah* shows at least that
there is and it sounds like it's even דאורייתא *de-oraisa* learned from
the פסוק *pasuk*. And but that's only after it hit the floor.
Again, this is quite ironic because normally, you know, once something is
נעשית מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* it doesn't turn on and off and on
and off, and that this that it re-ignites the קדושה *kedushah* is
a strange idea. So we'll see where the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to say. איכא דאמרי *ika d'amri* לימא מתניתין כרבי אליעזר בר צדוק
*leima matnitin ke-Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok*. Maybe our משנה *Mishnah* is like
רבי אליעזר בר צדוק *Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok*. Why? In this particular
scenario of the דאיקלט *iklat*, that again, same type of thing, that
you caught it and therefore it could be רבי אליעזר בר צדוק
*Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok*. אמרי *amrei*, again it's the texture of the...
if it hit the floor... No, no, it's still... still saying the
same thing. The אמרי *amrei* is the next answer. Again, the text
is a little is as you see, there's a lot of questions
as to how to read the text, you can just see by
all the notes. But anyway, the basic answer at the end here
is מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא *mi-d'rabbanan ve-kra asmakhta* מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan*. No, no, no,
maybe רבי אליעזר בר צדוק *Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok* when he says
there's מעילה *me'ilah*
by this wine, or I'm sorry, you have to burn this wine,
not
מעילה *me'ilah*, you have to burn this wine, he only means דרבנן
*de-rabbanan*. Really there's no מעילה *me'ilah*, נעשית מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato*, and when
he says you have to burn
the wine and
they would
burn it in the מקדש *Mikdash*, that's מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says והא קרא קנסב ליה *ve-ha kra ka-nasit leh*, he's quoting
פסוקים *psukim*? Alright, אסמכתא *asmakhta*, doesn't really... it's just a support. So
you have this opinion that he would burn the wine. Does that
prove the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that that shows that it still has
קדושה *kedushah*, which again make it an exception to נעשית מצותו *na'aseh
mitzvato*? תוספות *Tosafot* tries to say it's because it hit the floor,
and that's why it's a difference if you catch it in midair,
but in the end the גמרא *Gemara* seems to say that no,
maybe we could just say that that whole thing is מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan*
and really is נעשית מצותו *na'aseh mitzvato* and there's no longer a
מעילה *me'ilah* problem. So why is it דרבנן *de-rabbanan* and there is
a problem in this particular case... again for the same reason? Why
what? Why make a problem to begin with with this with these
clots of wine? According to רבי אליעזר בר צדוק *Rabbi Eliezer bar
Tzadok*? מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan*, yeah. It's not so clear, even though that he's
saying מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan* you burn it, it's not so clear he would
translate that as saying מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan* there's there's מעילה *me'ilah*. The גמרא
*Gemara* in the end says that he's our משנה *Mishnah*'s consistent with
him, and our משנה *Mishnah* says there is no מעילה *me'ilah* מדרבנן
*mi-d'rabbanan*. So all he's saying is look, gotta clean it out, what
do you do with it? You burn it. But that's not as
the end we're saying that that's מדרבנן *mi-d'rabbanan* he's not really saying
there is מעילה *me'ilah*. Why not use it for fertilizer? Oh, I
don't know, that's an interesting question. Okay, pick up tomorrow.